<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Vishnu Bharathi</title>
  
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://vishnubharathi.codes/"/>
  <updated>2020-07-19T14:52:28.266Z</updated>
  <id>https://vishnubharathi.codes/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Vishnu Bharathi</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Migrated my old blog posts from Medium</title>
    <link href="https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/migrated-my-old-blog-posts-from-medium/"/>
    <id>https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/migrated-my-old-blog-posts-from-medium/</id>
    <published>2020-07-19T14:30:04.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-07-19T14:52:28.266Z</updated>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        
        
          &lt;p&gt;Today I spent an hour or so in migrating my old blog posts present at medium.com to this site. Medium gave me a good playground to start blogging. I really appreciate it. But as time passed on, I understood that it is good to have control over our data and host it ourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medium is free to use. I mean, what really is free to use! The price I needed to pay for hosting my content on medium was to accept the big “sign up to medium” wall that they put on all of the blog posts. Also, they
        
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="blogging" scheme="https://vishnubharathi.codes/tags/blogging/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Short</title>
    <link href="https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/short/"/>
    <id>https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/short/</id>
    <published>2020-07-16T05:55:08.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-07-19T14:52:28.266Z</updated>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        
        
          &lt;p&gt;Every time I start a blog post, the words and ideas start playing around me and I just feel compelled to write down everything every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While long-form, detailed blog posts are great for describing ideas in depth, I have been wanting to write some short blog posts just like this
        
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="blogging" scheme="https://vishnubharathi.codes/tags/blogging/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Releasing sblog</title>
    <link href="https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/releasing-sblog/"/>
    <id>https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/releasing-sblog/</id>
    <published>2020-07-15T15:20:20.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-07-19T14:52:28.266Z</updated>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        
        
          &lt;p&gt;Today, I wrote a very simple utility that helps me kickstart new blog posts. In fact, this is the first blog post bootstrapped with the utility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have named it &lt;code&gt;sblog&lt;/code&gt; - short for “Start a new blog post”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It just saves a few seconds of my time and frees me from manually typing timestamps in my blog post headers everytime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been continously trying to bring down the friction in starting and publishing blog posts for a long time. This is probably a small
        
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="blogging" scheme="https://vishnubharathi.codes/tags/blogging/"/>
    
      <category term="automation" scheme="https://vishnubharathi.codes/tags/automation/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Under the hood of Go&#39;s context</title>
    <link href="https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/go-contexts/"/>
    <id>https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/go-contexts/</id>
    <published>2020-06-29T22:32:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-07-19T14:52:28.266Z</updated>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        
        
          &lt;p&gt;This post is dedicated to you if you had used the Go programming language and ever wondered “What is a context anyway?”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;context&lt;/code&gt; is a package in Go’s standard library. I think &lt;code&gt;context&lt;/code&gt; is idiomatic Go, hence I find quite some external packages and standard library packages using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read all about it from here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://golang.org/pkg/context/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://golang.org/pkg/context/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I am trying to
        
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="programming" scheme="https://vishnubharathi.codes/tags/programming/"/>
    
      <category term="go" scheme="https://vishnubharathi.codes/tags/go/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>You are building it for a million people</title>
    <link href="https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/rss-people/"/>
    <id>https://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/rss-people/</id>
    <published>2020-06-16T02:10:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-07-19T14:52:28.266Z</updated>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        
        
          &lt;p&gt;Earlier &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/rss-features&quot;&gt;I blogged a feature guide&lt;/a&gt; for building a new RSS feed reader application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering “But, who uses RSS readers anyway?” if you are new to RSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think RSS is a classic technology. It doesn’t get spoken about much. It feels like people are using it in silent or people aren’t using it at all. Because it feels relatively technical to setup RSS than setting up any other news app. For example, people may feel comfortable to
        
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="software" scheme="https://vishnubharathi.codes/tags/software/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
