<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vishnu Bharathi</title>
    <link>http://vishnubharathi.codes/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Vishnu Bharathi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 20:57:10 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://vishnubharathi.codes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Great Indian Developer Summit 2018</title>
      <link>http://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/great-indian-developer-summit-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 20:57:10 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/great-indian-developer-summit-2018/</guid>
      <description>Today, I attended GIDS18 (Great Indian Developer Summit). It spans 5 days with following topics covered.
 Web &amp;amp; Mobile Java &amp;amp; Dynamic Lang Data &amp;amp; Cloud Devops &amp;amp; Architecture Deep Dive  I thought of attending one day and learn about the trends in a specific topic. From my previous post you might have already guessed which one I had chosen.
I went for Java &amp;amp; Dynamic Lang!
Good morning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visit The Old To Understand The New</title>
      <link>http://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/visit-the-old-to-understand-the-new/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:55:12 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/visit-the-old-to-understand-the-new/</guid>
      <description>Today I made a firm choice. The choice that &amp;ldquo;I would dig deep into something and learn about it in detail&amp;rdquo;.
The Advice A few years back when I was still in college, I and my friend used to program in a computer science lab that was located near to the office of our teachers. Some teachers drop by sometime and speak with us about various things. Sometimes it would be about the cool new JavaScript framework that we are using in our project and sometimes it would just be about an interesting TV series or movie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quotes</title>
      <link>http://vishnubharathi.codes/quotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2018 07:32:13 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://vishnubharathi.codes/quotes/</guid>
      <description>Some words that inspire and help me.
 If you want to work on getting better, you need to start by knowing where you are.
 By: Aaron Swartz
Source: http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/semmelweis
 Embrace your failings. Be willing to believe the worst about yourself.
 By: Aaron Swartz
Source: http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/semmelweis
 Reverse your projections. Every time you see yourself complaining about other groups or other people, stop yourself and think: “is it possible, is there any way, that someone out there might be making the same complaints about me?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Beginnings</title>
      <link>http://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/the-beginnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2018 00:25:54 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://vishnubharathi.codes/blog/the-beginnings/</guid>
      <description>A few years back (around 2013), when I was still in college I started noticing few people sharing links to very interesting projects in my facebook feed. All the links pointed to this site called github.com. I was thrilled to open and read the README.md files every time I get the link to a project.
During those days, the best place to get software was sourceforge. At first, I didn&amp;rsquo;t quite get what GitHub is.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>